<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The meteors A sermon preached at a visitation. By Michael VVigmore, Rector of Thorseway in Lincolneshire, and sometimes Fellow of Oriel Colledge in Oxford</title>
            <author>Wigmore, Michael, 1588 or 9-1664?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15330</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25617</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119961</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855166</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855166</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20641</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15330)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20641)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1500:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The meteors A sermon preached at a visitation. By Michael VVigmore, Rector of Thorseway in Lincolneshire, and sometimes Fellow of Oriel Colledge in Oxford</title>
                  <author>Wigmore, Michael, 1588 or 9-1664?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper, for Nathaniel Butter, and are to be sold at his shop at the Pyde Bull, neere S. Austins Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20641:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20641:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE METEORS. A SERMON PREACHED AT A <hi>VISITATION.</hi> By MICHAEL VVIGMORE, Rector of <hi>Thorſeway</hi> in Lincolneſhire, and ſometimes Fellow of Oriel Colledge in <hi>Oxford:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Let your Light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie your Father which is in heaven,</hi>
               <bibl> Mat. 5. 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device or cast ornament of a head framed by two branches (not in McKerrow)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by THOMAS HARPER, for <hi>Nathaniel Butter,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Pyde Bull, neere S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Gate. 1633.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20641:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20641:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, THOMAS Lord <hi>Coventry,</hi> Baron of <hi>Aylesborough,</hi> Lord Keeper of the Great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> one of his Majeſties moſt Honourable Privie Councell, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch is the <hi>Leproſie</hi> of <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> that ſcarce <note place="margin">Luke 17.</note> one in ten comes backe to be thankfull: and God ſeemes to give a checke to mans nature, in placing <hi>Memory</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind in the head, as being an <hi>Embleme</hi> of our dulneſſe, in rendring the <hi>Offices</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20641:3"/> 
               <hi>of Gratitude.</hi> I muſt, and ever will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to Gods glory, and your Honour, that as I had my <hi>being</hi> from above, ſo have I my <hi>bene eſſe</hi> from your <hi>bounty,</hi> in ſo much that (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Philemon) I owe unto you even mine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Philem. 19.</note> 
               <hi>owne ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With that <hi>Samaritan</hi> in the Goſpell, <note place="margin">Luc. 17. 15. 16.</note> I am at length <hi>come backe againe to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> and to preſent you with theſe <hi>falſe fires,</hi> to make my <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible; <hi>ut Dei, ita eſt eorum qui Dei in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rex Platon.</note> 
               <hi>vices obeunt, pro ſua immenſitate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficia largiri, ſed hominum gratitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ex eorum modulo aestimare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Long hath <hi>mine heart burnt within me,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 39. 3.</note> with an earneſt, <hi>Quid retribuam?</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard <note place="margin">Pſal. 116. 12.</note> of thoſe gratious encouragements, by your <hi>Honour</hi> conferd upon me. Nor have I ſlept in the <hi>Land of forgetfulneſſe,</hi> but waited <hi>opportunity</hi> to vent my ſelfe;
<pb facs="tcp:20641:3"/> and now I have borrowed ſo much <hi>ſtrength</hi> of <hi>boldneſſe,</hi> as to lift up the <hi>eyes of Hope,</hi> preſuming to prefer theſe <hi>flaſhes</hi> to your view; in the which as the <hi>bad-borrowers</hi> of theſe dayes, I doe pay my <hi>great debts</hi> by <hi>ſmall Penſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this mine Adventure ſhall finde ſuch admittance, as to give the leaſt life to my riper ſtudies, I ſhall not ſuffer my <hi>Temples to reſt,</hi> till I be delivered of a <note place="margin">Pſal. 132. 4.</note> ſtronger birth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Coelum quietem ſortitur in motu,</hi> I ſhal ever account it my heaven upon earth, to labour to ſhew forth my thankfulnes, and to pray with a <hi>flaming heart, that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49. 22. 26.</note> 
               <hi>the bleſsing of Ioſeph</hi> light upon you.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Decem.</hi> 15. 1632.</date>
               <signed>Your Honours humble <hi>Eleemoſynarie,</hi> MICHAEL WIGMORE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20641:4"/>
            <head>Ad Lectorem.</head>
            <p>CVm carpuntur vitia, &amp; inde ſcandalum oritur, ipſe ſibi ſcandali cauſa eſt, qui fecit quod argui debet, non ille qui arguit. Bernard. Epiſt. 78.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20641:4"/>
            <head>THE METEORS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>MAT. 5. 14.</bibl>
               <q>You are the Light of the World.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Roems, they are like <hi>Cypreſſe trees, long,</hi> but <hi>fruitleſſe,</hi> and as he, 2 Macc. 2. 32. <hi>It is but a vaine thing to make a long Prologue. and to be ſhort in the ſtory it ſelfe:</hi> Then briefly to the matter we are to treat of.</p>
            <p>As we finde in Naturall Philoſophy, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, Lumen</hi> and <hi>Illuminatum;</hi> the <hi>Sunne</hi> the <hi>Treaſurer</hi> of <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Time,</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> of the Starres derived from the Sunne, and the <hi>Light</hi> of the Aire proceeding from them both: So ſhee (being the Handmaid to Divinity) <hi>holds out the glaſſe to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 12. 13.</note> 
               <hi>ſhow us the ſhadow of that we ſhall know, even as we are known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, Chriſt,</hi> to be that <hi>Sunne of Righteouſneſſe,</hi> foretold un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diviſion.</hi> Verſe 2. V. 3. leſ. 9. 1.</note> us in the fourth of Malachy. <hi>Secondly, his Diſciples</hi> to bee thoſe <hi>Starres</hi> ſpoken of in the twelfth of Daniel. <hi>And third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thoſe people that walk in darkneſſe, and that dwell in the</hi> Land of the ſhadow of death, to be that <hi>Medium illuminatum,</hi> looking for the light to ſhine upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Firſt,</hi> as in the firſt of Geneſis, the <hi>Light</hi> was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <note place="margin" type="runSum">I Part The light of Chriſt ſeene from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</note> before the <hi>Sunne:</hi> ſo was Chriſt knowne in the dayes of <note place="margin"> Pſal. 18. 9.</note> Old, before the Sunne of Righteouſneſſe was riſen, before He appeared in our <hi>Horoſcope,</hi> before <hi>He bowed the Heavens and came downe to</hi> cloath himſelfe in the fleſh of Man;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20641:5"/> 
               <hi>His light was then like the Birth of the Morning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Prophets,</hi> they beheld this Light, <hi>that a Virgin ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ieſ 71 14.</note> 
               <hi>and beare a Childe which ſhould be Emanuel,</hi> God with us: The <hi>Gentiles,</hi> they beheld this Light, witneſſe <hi>Zoroaſtes, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius Triſmegiſtus,</hi> the <hi>Sybils,</hi> the <hi>Oracles of their</hi> owne gods, and to make their <hi>ignorance inexcuſable,</hi> they had the Prophets of truth amongſt them; <hi>Iob knew that his Redeemer lived,</hi> and <note place="margin">Iob 19 25. Num. 24. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Balaam</hi> could prophecie unto <hi>Balaak, that there ſhould come a Starre of Iacob, and riſe a Scepter out of Iſrael:</hi> The <hi>Patriarks</hi> they beheld this Light; <hi>Abraham, he ſaw this day, and reioyced and was glad</hi> and that <hi>Grandſire</hi> of all mankinde, was no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <note place="margin">Iohn 8. 56.</note> diveſted from his <hi>Robe</hi> of <hi>Innocencie,</hi> But this <hi>Day-ſpring</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luc. 1. 78. Gen. 3. 15. Ioh. 1 5.</note> 
               <hi>from on high did viſit him;</hi> With, the <hi>ſeede of the Woman, ſhall breake the Serpents head.</hi> And thus the <hi>Light ſhined in the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, as the Iſraelites for their Convoy had a <hi>Cloud</hi> by Day, and a <hi>Pillar</hi> by Night: ſo till the time of the comming of Chriſt, there was no <hi>Day</hi> without a <hi>Cloud,</hi> no <hi>Night</hi> ſo dark, but had ſome light in it. God being known from the worlds firſt being, by <hi>Viſions,</hi> and <hi>Oracles, Revelations,</hi> and <hi>Dreames,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bulling Decad.</hi> 1 <hi>Ser.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Tradition of doctrine,</hi> from hand to hand, untill the dayes of his ſervant <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was in the ſeventh generation from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and yet the Pen-man of the worlds Hiſtorie, for neere 2500. yeeres.</p>
            <p>So that <hi>Adam</hi> and the <hi>Patriarks,</hi> the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> they had all a glimmering of this light; they all <hi>foretold the comming of Chriſt, as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> they <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1 21. Mat 11. 13. Ezech. 4. 1. <hi>Keck. Phyſ. p</hi> 1. <hi>ex <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg.</hi> Iob 36. 32. Galat. 4 4. The light ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in Chriſts incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Pſal. 19. 5. 2 Cor. 3. 14. 15. Heb. 10. 10. Heb. 7. 12. Heb. 10. 1.</note> all prophecied <hi>unto Iohn who</hi> was the Precurſor, that <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtarre that was ſent to beare witneſſe of the Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus (as <hi>Hieruſalem upon a Brickbat;</hi> or the Acts of the <hi>Romans</hi> on the <hi>Shield of Aeneas)</hi> I have briefly ſet out unto you <hi>how God hid the Light in his Fiſt, untill hee commanded it to breake forth, untill the fulneſſe of time was come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then came the Bridegroome</hi> out of his chamber, rejoycing as a Gyant to runne his courſe. The <hi>Law</hi> that was the vaile of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> was taken away by the comming of Chriſt; The <hi>Sacrifice</hi> offered yeere by yeere, was aboliſhed in His offering once for all; <hi>The glory of the Prieſthood</hi> was tranſlated; <hi>All the</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20641:5"/> 
               <hi>ſhadowes</hi> of good things to come; they all vaniſh at his Luſtre; I <hi>am come</hi> (ſaith our Saviour of himſelfe) I <hi>am come a Light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 12. 46</note> 
               <hi>the</hi> World, that no <hi>Beleever</hi> ſhould abide in <hi>darkneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such is the glory of the Diety,</hi> brighter then the Lights of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; <note place="margin">The glory of this light. Ecclus. Ioel 1. 10.</note> His <hi>eyes ten</hi> thouſand times clearer then the <hi>Sun,</hi> and cloathed with unſpeakeable Majeſtie; <hi>That the earth doth quake before him, the heavens tremble, the Moone be darkned, and the ſtars withdraw their light.</hi> Then how ſhall ſinfull man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him, whoſe foundation is but duſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When Chriſt was transfigured</hi> upon the Mount, his <hi>Viſage</hi> there <note place="margin">Mat. 17. 2.</note> as glorious as the Sunne, and his <hi>cloathing</hi> as white as the <hi>Light,</hi> his Diſciples were afraid, and fell to the earth: <hi>When</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 9. 8. Revel 1. 9.</note> 
               <hi>he appeared in the way to Damaſcus, Saul</hi> was ſtricken blind with his Brightneſſe. And <hi>when Saint Iohn</hi> ſaw him in the Ile of <hi>Pathmos,</hi> in the likeneſſe of the Sonne of man, with a garment downe to his feet, his eyes being as a flaming fire, his feet as moulten braſſe, and his face ſhining as the Sun in his ſtrength, he fell downe at his feet for dead; <hi>In his preſence ſhall the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioel 2. 6.</note> 
               <hi>tremble, and the countenance of all waxe blacke:</hi> ſo that wee may ſay with thoſe men of <hi>Bethſhemiſh,</hi> whom God had <note place="margin">2 Sam 6 29.</note> ſmitten for looking in the Arke) <hi>who is able to ſtand before the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If thoſe that have <hi>knowledge</hi> live two lives, whereas others live but one, then doubtleſſe every man is halfe dead (like him <note place="margin">Luc. 10. v. 30.</note> that fell amongſt the theeves:) our <hi>underſtanding</hi> is unſinew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the <hi>powers of our ſoules</hi> are out of joynt: ſo dimd, whilſt we looke through the cloud of <hi>Nature,</hi> that wee ſee no better then <hi>he in the Goſpell,</hi> that could not diſcerne a man from a <note place="margin">Mar. 8. 24.</note> tree.</p>
            <p>But <hi>God</hi> who is rich in mercy towards us, frameth his <note place="margin">This glory opened in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables and ſimilies.</note> 
               <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> to our capacity, ſhewing his <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to our ſenſes, and that Man may know him in ſome meaſure, He will be knowne unto us as man, <hi>by his parts,</hi> as eyes, cares, and the like; his <hi>affections,</hi> as Anger, Love, and Sorrow; his <hi>Titles,</hi> as King, Lord, and Father, whereas He is infinite, incomprehenſible, that filleth full the heaven <note place="margin">Ier. 23. 24.</note> and the earth; <hi>Totum quod vides, totum quod non vides:</hi> And <hi>Chriſt</hi> to inſinuate himſelfe into us, to leave the deeper
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20641:6"/> impreſſion in our hearts, ſo often openeth himſelfe in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, that, were they as ſtrangers unto you, I could leade you into acquaintance with them, throughout the whole courſe of his Doctrine. Sometimes ſtiling himſelfe a <hi>Sower,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <note place="margin">Mat. 13. Ioh 10. 11. Mat. 9. 12. Ioh. 15. 1. Ioh. 10. 7. Ioh. 14. 6. Rom. 1. 20.</note> a <hi>Shepheard,</hi> ſometimes a <hi>Phyſitiar,</hi> ſometimes a <hi>Vine,</hi> ſometimes a <hi>Doore,</hi> ſometimes the <hi>Way, the truth, and the Life: Notioribus ignota diſcuntur, Spiritualia per ſimilitudines;</hi> as Gods eternall power and Godhead are ſeene and underſtood by his workes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> in the 68. Pſalme, being there to make a deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on how God was praiſed in his Sanctuarie; the fuller to ſet it forth to the Life (as the troope that leads before ſome Prince, <note place="margin">This Glory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled by Light. Ver. 25. 27.</note> awakens an earneſt expectation) doth marſhall out the array thereof, with the <hi>Singers</hi> going before, with the <hi>Minſtrels</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after, with the <hi>Damoſels</hi> in the midſt, playing with Timbrels, with little <hi>Benjamin</hi> their Ruler, with the <hi>Princes of Iuda</hi> their Councell, the <hi>Princes of Zabulon</hi> and the <hi>Princes of Nepthalie.</hi> And Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, intending to <note place="margin">1 Ioh 1. 1. &amp;c.</note> comprize a briefe abridgement of the whole ſcope and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpell, to <hi>extract</hi> and <hi>ſublimate the Quinteſſence thereof,</hi> rankes out a faire companie to walke before, and to rouſe up <hi>dull attention</hi> (like the Chaine that was tyed to the tongue of <hi>Mercurie,</hi> and faſtned to the eares of the people) with, <hi>that which was from the beginning,</hi> which we have heard, which we have ſeene, and our hands have handled of the word of Life. And againe, <hi>the Life was manifeſt,</hi> and we have ſeene it, and ſhew it unto you: And againe, <hi>that which we have</hi> ſeene and heard, that we write and declare unto you; untill at length he openeth this rich <hi>Cabinet,</hi> and ſhewes us this illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Gemme; <hi>That God is Light, and in him is no darkeneſſe:</hi> And thus (as <hi>Salomon</hi> in his Temple) He preſents you with a faire and beautifull entrie, as a preparative to your devotion, to ſtirre up a zealous admiration, and to wonder at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward glory, <hi>That God is Light, and in Him is no darkneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plato</hi> and the heathen Philoſophers (that were directed by the eye of nature) <hi>viderunt illi ſuiſque literis copioſiſſime manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt, hinc illos unde &amp; nos fieri beatos, obiecto quodam lumine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Civit. Dei l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>intelligibili, quod Deus eſt illis</hi> (as ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine:)</hi> Hence
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20641:6"/> the Prophets were named Seers; and <hi>mens humana patibilis dicitur</hi> (as <hi>Zab.</hi> in his tract <hi>de mente agente) becauſe our Light</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>is from above, and commeth down from the Father of Lights:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve <note place="margin">Ioh. 12 36.</note> therefore in the Light, that ye may be children of the Light.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Light</hi> was the firſt borne of all things viſible: ſo was it <note place="margin">Chriſt the Light.</note> not without a myſtery, that for the diſtinction of the ſix firſt dayes, God cloſed them up with this phraſe of ſpeech, <hi>The Evening and the Morning were the firſt day; and the Evening and the Morning were the ſecond day;</hi> and ſo on in the reſt of the dayes: whereas <hi>Nature</hi> gives the birthright to the <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> But he foreſeeing in his infinite preſcience, that wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man within few houres ſhould caſt himſelfe headlong into darkeneſſe, doth intimate unto us thereby, that <hi>firſt</hi> ſhould be <hi>the Night</hi> of mans miſery, and then ſhould follow the <hi>Day</hi> of our redemption by ſending of his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus, God of God, Light of Light, very God of very God: And <hi>This light was that true light which lighteth every</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh 1. 19.</note> 
               <hi>man that comes into the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all the <hi>Metaphors</hi> the world affords, none ſo fit an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of Chriſt, as <hi>Light,</hi> which is the <hi>ioy of the eyes, and the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 13. 30.</note> 
               <hi>true comforter of the heart,</hi> although continuance and aſſiduity makes us behold it with leſſe admiration.</p>
            <p>Amongſt thoſe foure good <hi>Mothers</hi> that doe nurſe and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>an.</hi> of the eye <hi>cap.</hi> 4. The excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Light</note> cheriſh up foure bad daughters; as <hi>Vertue, Envy; Peace,</hi> I <hi>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> and <hi>Truth Hatred; Familiarity</hi> brings forth <hi>Contempt.</hi> And hence it is (as one well obſerves) that thoſe things which we moſt feare and reverence, are moſt removed from our ſight: <hi>Perſeverantia conſuetudinis amiſit admirationem.</hi> the daily uſe of this glorious creature doth make it the leſſe to be admired. When King and Keſar, old and yong, high and low, rich and poore, all deſire it alike.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Light,</hi> it diſplaieth it ſelfe to all creatures, and it is trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed in an inſtant. It pierceth every tranſparent body, and is not defiled with any uncleanneſſe: It is the conduit of all heavenly vertues, and is the quickner of all that is: It actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ateth all colours: It is the mother of all beauties: It giveth life to all the ornaments, to all the delights that the world
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20641:7"/> affords us. <hi>The Light is ſweet, and a pleaſant thing it is for the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccles 11. 7.</note> 
               <hi>eyes to looke upon the Sunne:</hi> And, <hi>ſi dulce eſt lumen hoc mundi, quanto erit dulcius lumen gloriae. Si delectabile eſt videre ſolem creatum, quanto erit delectabilius ſolem videre increatum, creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſolis Creatorem.</hi> I am the light of the world (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>Ioh</hi> 8 12. And therefore it was (as ſome obſerve) that Chriſt was borne when the dayes were at ſhorteſt, <hi>ut diminuto noctis curriculo, defectionem ſentiant opera tenebrarum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this comfortable nature of the light, upon any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of <hi>ioy</hi> and <hi>deliverance</hi> (to ſhew how <hi>beautifull are the feet of them that bring glad tidings of ſalvation)</hi> wee decke it forth with her <hi>glory,</hi> naming the <hi>time pro qualitate rei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Lepers</hi> (in the ſecond of Kings, <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 9.) in the <hi>Night</hi> that they found the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> were fled, wee doe not well (ſay they one to another) we doe not well to hold our peace, this <hi>Day</hi> is a <hi>Day</hi> to bring glad tidings: And that wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <note place="margin">Luc. 2. 11.</note> Angell in the Goſpell when he came to the Shepherds in the <hi>Night</hi> of the Nativity, This <hi>Day</hi> (ſaith hee) in the City of David is borne a Saviour which is Chriſt the Lord. Then did <hi>the Night ſhine as the Day,</hi> becauſe the Sunne of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe <note place="margin">Pſal. 139. 12.</note> was riſen; as <hi>there was darkneſſe at the houre of his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amos 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi>death,</hi> for then the Sunne did ſet at the noone-tide.</p>
            <p>And yet Chriſt here (as <hi>Moſes</hi> elſe where) hath a vaile <note place="margin">Light but a ſhadow to Chriſt. Pſal. 104. 2.</note> put over his face, to whom the <hi>Light is but as a garment,</hi> or as a <hi>curtaine</hi> drawne over his glory, to bee a ſhadow of his eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and being. If the Light bee Darkneſſe, how great is that Darkneſſe? But when Light and Luſtre, and Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Glory, and Majeſty ſhall be but ſhadowes; how great is the Brightneſſe, and the Luſtre, and the Light of the glory of that Majeſty which <hi>dwelleth in the light that none can attaine unto.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim 6. 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is reported concerning <hi>Noah,</hi> that whilſt the window of the Arke was ſhut, he made uſe of ſome <hi>reſplendent ſtone,</hi> by whoſe raies the objects of the ſight preſented themſelves to the organ of the eye. However the conjecture be but cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, yet true it is that Chriſt is that <hi>Stone,</hi> which albeit the <note place="margin">Mat. 21 42.</note> builders refuſed, is now become the head-ſtone of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; at whoſe approach the light of the Moone became un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Ieſ 30. 26.</note>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:20641:7"/> us as the light of the Sunne; ſalvation became the wals of <note place="margin">Ieſ 60. 18. &amp;c.</note> our Church, and her gates the praiſe of God; the Lord our everlaſting light, and the Sunne that ſhall never ſet, <hi>Lux De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us illuſtris illuminans omnia, aliae luces tanquam micae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus farre of that <hi>Lux innata,</hi> that <hi>true Light,</hi> that <hi>Light</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh 1. 9. &amp; 8. 11. &amp; 9. 5. &amp; 1 Ioh. 1. 5.</note> 
               <hi>of life,</hi> that <hi>Light of the world, in whom is no darkneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am now come to my ſecond chapter, and to ſpeake of that <hi>Lumen,</hi> that <hi>Lux infuſa,</hi> whereby wee are enlightned <note place="margin" type="runSum">2 Part. The Light de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from Chriſt to his Miniſters.</note> from above (as the <hi>Starres</hi> doe borrow their <hi>light</hi> from the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Sunne.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zanchius</hi> in his worke <hi>De operibus Dei,</hi> upon thoſe words, Gen. 1. <hi>Sint luminaria in expa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſione coelorum,</hi> obſerves that <hi>lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minare differt à luce, ſicut candela à luce quam habet;</hi> and puts the nature of the <hi>Starres</hi> and the <hi>Light,</hi> at as farre diſtance one from the other, as the inſtrument that holds the light differs from the light that it ſuſtaineth. And as God is the light that dwelleth in you, ſo you my brethren of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, you are <hi>Luminaria,</hi> the Inſtruments of light to <hi>ſhine in the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 15.</note> 
               <hi>middeſt of a crooked generation.</hi> Thus he which is <hi>the light of the world,</hi> Iohn 8. 12. hath appointed <hi>you to bee the light of the world,</hi> Mat. 5. 14. and he which is <hi>the bright morning Starre,</hi> Revel. 22. 16. hath <hi>given you the morning ſtarre, as he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Father,</hi> Revel. 2. 28. to bee as that <hi>ſtarre</hi> that <note place="margin">Mat 2. 9.</note> appeared in the Eaſt, and that <hi>led to the place where the child lay.</hi> Chriſt beholding from the heighth of his Sanctuary, the condition of his Church here on earth, how that after the dayes of his fleſh, they ſhould be <hi>as ſheepe having no Shepherd;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 9. 36. Eph. 4. 11. 12.</note> he hath given ſome <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ſome <hi>Prophets,</hi> ſome <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> and ſome to be <hi>Shepherds</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> to the gathering together of the Saints, to the worke of the Miniſtration, and to the building up of his body. And as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> when they came to <hi>Elim,</hi> found there <hi>twelve Fountaines,</hi> and <hi>ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Num. 33. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Palme trees:</hi> ſo the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> as <hi>twelve Fountaines,</hi> have flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over all the face of the earth; and the <hi>ſeventy Diſciples</hi> as <hi>ſeventy Palmetrees,</hi> have flouriſhed, and ſpred over all the <note place="margin">Luc. 10. 1.</note> the world, rayſing up new ſeed in the Church, by Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from Chriſt, Impoſition of hands, and Succeſſion Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall <note place="margin">Acts 6. 6. 2 Tim. 1. 6.</note> throughout all ages.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:20641:8"/>
            <p>You, my Brethren, are brancht from theſe; you are the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 1. 1 Cor. 3. 9. Luc 12. 42. 1 Pet. 2. 9. 1 Tim 2 7. Gal 4. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Diſpoſers</hi> of the ſecrets of God; you are his <hi>Labourers,</hi> and his <hi>Builders;</hi> you are his wiſe and faithfull <hi>Stewards,</hi> whom the Lord hath made Rulers over his houſhold; Yea, you are his <hi>honourable Prieſthood;</hi> yea, his <hi>Embaſſadors;</hi> yea, his <hi>Angels.</hi> You, even you are the Light of the world; <hi>Et ſic dicebat Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuis, vos eſtis lux mundi, cum ipſe ſolus eſſet vera lux,</hi> as <hi>Beza</hi> in his notes upon the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> tels us in his Ethicks, that <hi>Bonum</hi> is <hi>Verum,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt Eth. l</hi> 1. Lights diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed. Meteors divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> 
               <hi>Apparens:</hi> and there are certaine <hi>Apparitions,</hi> which for the <hi>ſemblance</hi> that they have with the <hi>Light,</hi> doe ſeeme to be of the ſame nature. Theſe being proper to the <hi>Aire,</hi> ſome there are in the <hi>higher region</hi> as are <hi>Cometa,</hi> and <hi>Caprae Saltantes;</hi> others in the <hi>middle,</hi> as <hi>Tonitru and Fulgur;</hi> and there are walking in the <hi>lower region, Ignis Fatuus,</hi> and <hi>Ignis Lambens; Oppoſita iux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſe poſita magis eluce ſcunt,</hi> and therefore Ile begin with theſe, that thoſe other in their order may appeare the clearer.</p>
            <p>Firſt of the <hi>Comete,</hi> that prodigious Light, ſhewing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, <note place="margin">Cometa.</note> and the death of Kings: ſuch is the nature of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane Iupiter</hi> ſtiled the ſervant of the ſervants of God, when he meanes to <hi>exalt himſelfe as an Eagle, and to towre amongſt the ſtars</hi> nipping the Chriſtian Princes in the crownes, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <note place="margin">Obad. verſe 4. K. of defen. of the right of Kings. Exod. 32 22. 1 Sam. 15. 30. 31. 35. Baruc 1. 11.</note> Cheque mate to the greateſt Monarchs, &amp; ſpilling their bloud like water on the ground. Whereas, <hi>Aaron</hi> ſubmitted to <hi>Moſes, Let not the wrath of my Lord waxe fierce. Samuel</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured <hi>Saul</hi> a Reprobate, mourning for him at his funerall Exequies. And the <hi>Captive Iewes</hi> in <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſent to the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> to pray for the life of <hi>Nabuchedonozor,</hi> and for the welfare of <hi>Baltaſar</hi> his ſonne; how then can that Church, that Body, chooſe but be full of mortall diſeaſes, when the Head is ſo full of peccant humours.</p>
            <p>It was enacted by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that a man that <note place="margin">Deut. 21. 12.</note> would marry a Captive woman, ſhould ſhave her head, and pare his nailes, and put away her old rayment from her. We will apply it to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> Let her put away her ſuperfluities, let her lay aſide her old corruptions; Let her leave off her ſuperſtitious Reliques, and <hi>we two will be one fleſh;</hi> ſhe ſhall be unto us an <hi>Iſraelite:</hi> And that great Monarch of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20641:8"/> great Babylon, <hi>Luminare mains</hi> (as he ſtiles himſelfe) that <hi>Stella Crinita,</hi> that <hi>Blazing ſtarre,</hi> whoſe <hi>haires are growne like</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 33.</note> 
               <hi>the Eagles feathers, and his nailes like the clawes of Harpyes;</hi> let him lift up his eyes to heaven, ſo that his <hi>underſtanding</hi> be reſtored, and wee will joyne our ſelves unto him, to bring him to his former Beauty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Capraeſaltantes</hi> are another kind of <hi>Meteor,</hi> ſtrugling in the <note place="margin">Capraeſaltan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> bowels of our own Church, like <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> in the womb of <hi>Rebecca,</hi> or the <hi>Huſſits</hi> and the <hi>Thaborits</hi> amongſt the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemians,</hi> onely differing <hi>per magis &amp; minus:</hi> Men that for ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and for Conſcience, might worthily ſhine as the ſtars in the firmament. But that (as it is generally obſerved) <hi>Stella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nulla per ſe movetur ſuum dividendo orbem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, it might make us to mourne and bleed, to ſee how <note place="margin">Iudg. 5. 15.</note> for the <hi>diviſions</hi> of <hi>Levi,</hi> there are ariſen <hi>great thoughts of heart.</hi> To ſee our ſelves to be parted into companies, like unto the Sheep and Goats of <hi>Laban,</hi> ſome browne, and ſome beſpeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: <note place="margin">Gen 30. 32.</note> to ſee how (like that Monſter in <hi>Plinie,</hi> that <hi>Amphiſbaena,</hi> that hath two heads) we ſtrive one with another for Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, whilſt our enemies ſtand by and behold it with, <note place="margin">Pſal. 35. 25. 2 Sam. 1. 20.</note> 
               <hi>There, there, ſo would we have it;</hi> Oh, let it not be told in <hi>Gath,</hi> let it not be publiſhed in <hi>Askalon,</hi> leſt the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and the uncircumciſed have cauſe to triumph.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccleſia eſt illud corpus Chriſti quod charius habuit, quam quod tradidit morti;</hi> let us not lacerate, and teare it to pieces, with our unprofitable litigations; let us not be of a <hi>viperous genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to eate our way through our mothers bowels; let us not rend Chriſts ſeameleſſe Garment, which muſt be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mea,</hi> or not <hi>Tunica;</hi> let us put up our angry pens, and as <hi>Curtius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports <note place="margin">Q Curt.</note> of thoſe people that were ever in armes one with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet when <hi>Alexander</hi> came upon them, <hi>quos alias bellare inter ſe ſolitos, tunc periculi ſocietas iunxerat:</hi> ſo let us bend our ſwords and our ſpeares againſt the breſt of the common enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He,</hi> even he whoſe name is <hi>wonderfull,</hi> the giver of <hi>counſell,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ieſ. 9. 5.</note> the <hi>mighty God,</hi> the <hi>everlaſting Father,</hi> the <hi>Prince of peace,</hi> would not have us awaken his Beloved, whilſt he doth reſt his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed <note place="margin">Can. 2 8. &amp; 5. 2</note> locks upon the lap of the ſleeping Church: <hi>Remember</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20641:9"/> what <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid to <hi>Lot,</hi> and remember that we are Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <note place="margin">Gen. 13. 8. Eph 4. 3.</note> and therefore bound in the bond of <hi>peace,</hi> for the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Vnitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the <hi>Ditty</hi> of our Saviours <hi>Birth-Song, peace on earth,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luc. 2. 14.</note> 
               <hi>good will towards men;</hi> It was his <hi>Legarie</hi> to his <hi>Diſciples, My peace I give you, my peace I leave you:</hi> And it is the daily <hi>prayer</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 14. 27.</note> of his <hi>Spouſe, da pacem,</hi> give peace in our time O Lord: <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> (be the <hi>Garden</hi> never ſo faire, be the <hi>Intention</hi> never ſo ſincere) twill make the world to be miſdoubtfull, and to feare a <hi>Snake</hi> under every <hi>Leafe:</hi> Then let there be no diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongſt us, and let us <hi>proceede by one Rule, that we may be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>of one accord;</hi> leſt when that <hi>Great Shepheard</hi> of our ſoules ſhall <note place="margin">1 Pet 2 25. &amp; 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mat. 25. 41.</note> come to ſeparate the <hi>Goats</hi> from the <hi>Sheepe,</hi> he brand us with an <hi>Ite maledicti, Depart ye curſed into everlaſting fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am next to ſpeake of the <hi>Belly</hi> of that <hi>Image,</hi> whoſe <hi>Head</hi> is <hi>ambition,</hi> whoſe <hi>armes, diſſention;</hi> I am now in the <hi>middle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tonitru &amp; Fulgur.</hi> Mat. 3. 17.</note> where I meet with <hi>Tonitru,</hi> and <hi>Fulgur, Boanerges,</hi> ſons of <hi>Thunder;</hi> who though they be of a lower Region, yet are they of a hotter conſtitution; well may they be the <hi>ſalt of the earth,</hi> but of ſuch a <hi>Peetriſh</hi> and fierce nature, that touch them <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 13.</note> with the leaſt ſparke of <hi>admonition,</hi> and theyle be ready to flaſh in your faces: Theſe men inflamed <hi>per Antiperiſtaſin,</hi> by ſeeing <hi>Iudah</hi> frozen on his dregges, may ſay as <hi>David</hi> in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde, <hi>That</hi> to keep ſilence, it was paine and griefe, <hi>That</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 39. 3.</note> their very heart waxt hot within them, <hi>That</hi> while they were thus muſing, the fire kindled, untill (like ſo many Canons overcharged, or as <hi>Lightning</hi> choakt up in a cloud of <hi>Thunder,</hi> they give a terrible cracke about our eares) <hi>untill at length,</hi> they ſpeake with their tongues, recoyling againſt order and Diſcipline.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>—feriuntque ſummos</hi> 
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fulmina montes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>They would have a ſpotleſſe congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, looking for a <hi>Moone, ſine macula,</hi> ſeeking a <hi>Church</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Blemiſh,</hi> and thus forgetting themſelves to be ſinners, they doe with <hi>Calisto</hi> in the <hi>Metamorphoſis,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Saepe feris latuit viſis oblita quid eſſet; </l>
               <l>Vrſaque conſpectos in montibus horruit urſes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ovid Met. l.</hi> 2.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Whereas the <hi>Fleſh</hi> luſteth againſt the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 17.</note>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:20641:9"/> againſt the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> ſo that we cannot doe what we would; we can but indevour to that which is before, wee can no more <note place="margin">Phil. 3 13. 14.</note> here but preſſe towards the marke; <hi>perfectionem in hac vita ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quimur, aſſequimur in futura.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being thus puft up with an undiſcreet zeale, their <hi>Pulpit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tacit.</note> like the <hi>Tribunall</hi> of <hi>Caſſius,</hi> it doth become <hi>ſcopulus reorum,</hi> a Rocke, a Shipwracke to a tender conſcience; affording no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the curſings of <hi>Mount Ebal,</hi> nothing but the <hi>thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 17. 13. Exod. 19. 18.</note> and <hi>lightnings</hi> of <hi>Sinai.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is obſerved in the motion of the Sphaeres, if they ſhould not be ſtayd and ſlackned by the contrary courſe of the <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum mobile.</hi> that they would ſet the whole on fire. And it is true in the nature of <hi>zeale,</hi> not being moderated with <hi>diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> it ſoone ſets all in a combuſtion, <hi>Fervor diſcretionem erigat,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; diſcretio Fervorem dirigat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God that made all things with the breath of his mouth, and accompliſhed his ſixe dayes worke in the <hi>temperate</hi> ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the <hi>Equinoctiall,</hi> appeared to <hi>Adam</hi> in the coole of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zanch de oper. creat. part</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. Pſal. 104. 4. <hi>Zanch ubi ſupra.</hi> Ionah 4. 1. &amp;c.</note> day: He that made his Angels ſpirits, and his Miniſters a fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire; when he made the Light and the Stars, tempered the Light with moiſture, and made the Stars of a watry ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. And though he be a God of vengeance, yet when the rebellious Prophet <hi>Ionah</hi> had ſo much the <hi>over-flowing</hi> of the <hi>Gall,</hi> as to be angry with his dreadfull power, he reprehends him with as much indulgence, as if the tendreſt father in the world were to deale with his deareſt ſonne; <hi>and ſhall we bruſe the broken reede, ſhall we quench the ſmoaking flaxe? Oh let the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12 20. Pſal. 141. 5.</note> 
               <hi>righteous correct me friendly,</hi> but let not their precious <hi>balmes</hi> breake mine head; let us handle the wounds of our Brethren with <hi>gentleneſſe,</hi> and the <hi>Bowels of compaſſion:</hi> let us bring <hi>pitty</hi> in our eyes and hearts, when we chance to ſee their fals and infirmities: <hi>and let us remember</hi> the rule of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Gal. 6. 1 <hi>Brethren, if any man be prevented in ſinne, yee then which are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, reſtore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meekeneſſe, conſidering thy ſelfe, leſt thou alſo be tempted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the <hi>Snuffes</hi> of the former <hi>Lights,</hi> ſending forth <note place="margin">Ignis Fatuus.</note> an unſavory ſmell out of the lowermoſt <hi>Socket</hi> of the <hi>Ayre;</hi> Firſt to ſpeake of <hi>Ignis Fatuus,</hi> or the <hi>Lay-Elder;</hi> here like
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20641:10"/> unto ſome <hi>ſimple Swaine</hi> at a portentous and prodigious <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teor,</hi> ſeldome ſeene in the world of his <hi>Hemiſphere,</hi> ſo I cannot but <hi>ſtand at a gaze,</hi> to ſee the <hi>Starres</hi> to drop from the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to ſee the <hi>light</hi> to be turned into darkneſſe, to ſee the <hi>Prieſts</hi> to be cloathed with ſhame, ſo many and ſo well nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured, that have ſuckt milke with us from the ſame breſts, to be miſ-led into that diſcipline, by the which an <hi>Artificer</hi> may be made an <hi>Elder,</hi> and of a <hi>Tradſman</hi> become a <hi>Church-man:</hi> We may lament them with the wife of <hi>Phinees,</hi> when <note place="margin">1 Sam 4. 21.</note> the <hi>Arke</hi> was taken by the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and ſhee named her child <hi>Ichabod, The glory of Iſrael is taken from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Ignis Fatuus,</hi> this <hi>Lay Brother,</hi> by their Impoſition of hands, ſhall have the miſleading of a <hi>Band</hi> of ſoules (as the Deuill the lunaticke in the Goſpell) ſometimes through fire, <note place="margin">Mar. 17. 15.</note> ſometimes through water; and yet (as <hi>Aventine</hi> once of ſome ſuch) <hi>Si praelati iſti plebei eſſent, nemo facile ipſis haram</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Avent. de reb. Tur. par.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>committeret, in illo vero ſtatu, &amp; arae, et animae hominum ipſorum fidei creduntur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was commanded by the <hi>Law Leviticall,</hi> that no blinde <note place="margin">Levit. 22. 22.</note> creature ſhould be offred to God; how then ſhall the blinde lead the blind, unleſſe it be <hi>in praecipitium?</hi> Like unto that <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſian</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Berg. Hiſt &amp; Faſc. Temp.</note> 
               <hi>Iew</hi> in the yeere of our Lord 450, who ſaying hee was <hi>Moſes</hi> ſent from heaven to conduct his brethren through the Sea into Iury (as before hee had done out of Aegypt) cauſed them to commit themſelves unto the waves, where they were all drowned like <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoſt.</p>
            <p>Yet theſe will torment a Text of Scripture, manage a long and monſtrous diſcourſe (conceived and borne in the ſame inſtant) wreſt and pervert the word of God, and inſtead of the naturall milke thereof, ſucke out the blood of miſ-interpretation, as farre diſtant from the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as was that ridiculous <hi>Actor</hi> in <hi>Smyrna,</hi> pronouncing <hi>O Coelum</hi> with his mouth, and with his finger pointing to the ground. The <hi>Copperſmith</hi> will be bold to controule <hi>Paul;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 14. Act. 19. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Demetrius the Silverſmith</hi> will oppoſe the whole Church, and the <hi>Cobler</hi> find fault with the thigh of the picture.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Frange leves calamos, &amp; ſcinde Thalia libelles, <note place="margin">Mart.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Si dare ſutori caloeus iſta poteſt.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20641:10"/>
            <p>There is a Rout of their followers, <hi>a generation</hi> deſcribed <note place="margin">The condition of the Faction. Pro. 30. 12.</note> by <hi>Solomon,</hi> that are pure in their owne eyes, and yet they are not waſhed from their ſinnes: Let me ſhew you the <hi>pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trait</hi> of them, as they are drawne out to the life by another, and ſo printed to the view of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They are</hi> (ſaith mine Author) <hi>the ſcumme of the Commons,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> Ser. True profeſſor.</note> 
               <hi>the tags and rags of the people, baſe mechanicks, men of little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, leſſe honeſty, and no diſcretion at all: In their attempts pragmaticall, in their humour phantaſticall, in their profeſſion Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaicall, in their bookes hypocriticall, in their opinions Anabaptiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, in their Doctrine ſchiſmaticall, in their words Angelicall, in their deeds Diabolicall.</hi> But what ſhould I tell you <hi>de aſini umbra,</hi> or hold you in diſcourſe of this Brainſicke Frie; Ile only haile <hi>Ignis lambent,</hi> and ſo weele ſtrike ſayle, and come a ſhore.</p>
            <p>Such is the nature of many men, that having ſome ſecret <note place="margin">Ignis Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens.</note> and beloved ſinne, which is as neere, as deere unto them, as was the ſonne of the Bondwoman to <hi>Abraham,</hi> when hee praied for his life and proſperity, <hi>Oh that Iſmael might live in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17 18.</note> 
               <hi>thy ſight.</hi> They can with <hi>Herod</hi> heare <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> ſo that hee would not touch upon <hi>Herodias:</hi> Theſe men are likened to <hi>Apes</hi> and <hi>Monkies,</hi> which breake the glaſſes that they looke into, becauſe they ſhew them their owne deformities: ſo that it often fals out with them as the Prophet ſpeakes, <hi>Zach,</hi> 11. 8. <hi>Three Shepherds I put out of office in one month, for I might not away with their doctrine:</hi> And yet for all <hi>Michah</hi> will <note place="margin">Iud. 17.</note> have his <hi>Levite.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Scit Comitem horridulum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rita donare lacerna, </l>
               <l>Et verum inquit amo, verum mihi dicito de me;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui pote?—</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Perſ. Sat.</hi> 5.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>How can that be? when they ſay unto <hi>the Seers, ſee not, and to them that be cleare of iudgement,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ieſ. 30. 10.</note> 
               <hi>looke not out right things for us,</hi> but ſpeake <hi>(placentia)</hi> leaſings unto us.</p>
            <p>As the Devill dealt with Chriſt when he tooke advantage <note place="margin">Mat. 4. 2.</note> of his hunger; ſo there want not unto theſe ſome that are left of the old houſe of <hi>Eli, that will come and crooch for a peece</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 36.</note> 
               <hi>of ſiluer, and to bee put in office amongſt the Prieſts;</hi> theſe men
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20641:11"/> may be compared to <hi>Surgeons,</hi> that though they have not the <hi>hearts of Lions</hi> to put their <hi>Probes</hi> home to the quicke, yet they have <hi>the hands of Ladyes</hi> enured to <hi>Complexions</hi> and <hi>Paintings,</hi> and to <hi>daube with untempered morter:</hi> to the <hi>Polypus</hi> that is ſo <note place="margin">Ezech. 13. 10. <hi>Aelian de var. hiſt. lib.</hi> 1. Eze. 13. 18. 19.</note> variable, taking the colour from the rocke he cleaves to: to thoſe <hi>Daughters of Hieruſalem,</hi> (or to thoſe roguing <hi>Gypſons</hi> of our times) <hi>that pollute the people, and kill their ſoules for hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Barly, and peeces of bread:</hi> to thoſe <hi>five and twenty men in the Prophet,</hi> that did turne their backs towards the Temple, <note place="margin">Ezech. 8. 16.</note> and worſhiped with their faces towards the Eaſt, caſting the word of God behinde them, and aiming at nothing but their <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 17.</note> owne riſing.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the <hi>Deuill</hi> in <hi>Samuels mantle, Ignis Lambens, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Paraſites, glavering Temporizers, Trencher Chaplains,</hi> that will <hi>lingere ſputum,</hi> become all things unto all men, ſo that they may pleaſe ſome men.</p>
            <p>It is an obſervation of <hi>Ioab,</hi> that though he were a valiant Captaine, yet was he not reckoned amongſt <hi>Davids</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, <note place="margin">1 Chron. 11.</note> becauſe hee betrayed <hi>Amaſa</hi> with a kiſſe: much leſſe <note place="margin">2 Sam. 2. 9.</note> ſhall the Lord of <hi>David</hi> write thoſe names in the Booke of Life, <hi>that kiſſe, and bite, and yet cry peace,</hi> like thoſe Prophets <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 3.</note> in the third of <hi>Micheas, ver.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>He whoſe <hi>Lip</hi> is full of indignation, his <hi>Tongue</hi> a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <note place="margin">Ieſ 30. ver. 17. 30. 33.</note> fire, and his <hi>Breath</hi> like a river of Brimſtone, ſhall cauſe his glorious voyce to be heard, and ſhall declare his ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out arme againſt thoſe that have ſweet tongues, and make the people erre by their flatteries. <note place="margin">Ier. 23 31. 32.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And this be ſpoken of thoſe <hi>Meteors</hi> that do hang betwixt Heaven and Earth: I ſhould now come to the <hi>Angels of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Concluſion. Revel. 1. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Churches,</hi> thoſe <hi>Starres</hi> that are in the right hand of him that ſtood in the middeſt of the <hi>Golden Candleſticke;</hi> but then I ſhould overflow my ſands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Like a Labourer</hi> I have digged the foundation, and I have <note place="margin">1 Cor. 39. 10. 11.</note> laid it upon Chriſt Ieſus; I have removed all the <hi>Rubbiſh</hi> in the deſcription of theſe <hi>Apparitions;</hi> I have (I hope) made a faire way for ſome other <hi>(Aholiab</hi> or <hi>Bezaleel)</hi> for the finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the reſt of the <hi>Building.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 31. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20641:11"/>
            <p>Now being cut off by the tyranny of Time, Ile end as I began out of 2 Macc. <hi>If I have done well, I have done what I</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cap. 15. ver. 38</note> 
               <hi>ſhould; if otherwiſe, it is the beſt I could,</hi> (and according to the time allotted unto me:) In the meane while <hi>conſider what is ſaid, and the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Lord give you underſtanding in all things.</hi> Amen. <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:20641:12"/>
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>December</hi> 16. 1632.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>PErlegi hanc concionem cui titulus <hi>(A Sermon preached at a Viſitation in</hi> Lincolneſhire, <hi>by</hi> Michael Wigmore, <hi>Rector of</hi> Thorſeway <hi>in</hi> Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colneſhire, <hi>and ſometime Fellow of</hi> Oriell <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in</hi> Oxford) una cum Epiſtolâ nuncupatoria ad honoratiſsim. Dom. Magni Sigill. Cuſtod. qui quidem liber continet paginas 15. in quibus nihil reperio bonis moribus aut ſanae doctrinae contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, aut quicquam aliud quo minus cum utilitate publicâ <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> modo intra tres menſes proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſequentes typis mandetur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Gulielmus Haywood,</hi> Epiſco. Londin. Capell. domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20641:12"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
